..:: YOLO - Your
Source Of Quality::..
Pandora's forests
hold many dangers.
But the most dangerous
thing about Pandora is…
that you can come to
like her too much.
We sing the chords to remember.
Each pearl is a story from our life.
A gem for the birth of our son.
Not finished!
A gem for our adopted
daughter, Kiri, -
- born of Grace's avatar, -
- and whose conception
was a complete mystery.
A gem for the first
meeting with Eywa.
The people say we
live in Eywa, -
- and Eywa lives in us.
The almother takes care
of all her children.
Happiness is straightforward.
Think a toad like
me would find it.
The first time I met your
father, I tried to kill him.
Love at first sight.
Before I knew it, we had four.
We sent the sky people back to
Earth, but some stayed here.
Scientists who were
loyal to the Na'vi.
And then there was Spider.
He was trapped here.
Too young for a cryocapsule.
The war had taken his parents, so
he was raised by the scientists.
He was like a stray cat
that kept coming running.
He and our kids
were inseparable.
To Neytiri he would always
be a stranger. One of them.
He belongs among his own.
- I had it first!
- Why do you have to have it?
I was a few years away from having
the language hammered into the tuber.
But now it comes
naturally to me.
I hate you!
I hate you to no end,
Lo'ak! Crazy face!
Whoa, that's good. Soon
firewood falls down.
He immediately emerges from
the rocks. There he is.
Like, take it.
Neteyam, the great
fisherman. Good boy.
- It's a big crab.
- By the stones, as you said.
- How tall is he? - So tall.
Time flies. Like a dream.
- Kiri. - Come here, bro.
Smile, skxawng.
Happiness is straightforward.
It can be a date night
without children.
There's just that about luck...
that it can end abruptly.
A new star in the night sky.
That could only mean one thing.
Ships slowing down.
The Sky People had returned.
A YEAR LATER
The pulse rises.
They'll probably make
it. Take it easy.
Good pupillary reaction.
Remove it there.
Colonel, can you hear me?
Please lie down.
- Stun him! - Hurry up!
- Call the guards! - Grab him!
Hold him! Calm down, Colonel!
It's me, Corporal Wainfleet!
Lyle? Is it you?
Yes, and Z Dog.
And Fig.
Just let me go. I'm
completely calm.
It didn't matter.
Attention. Two minutes
to land on Pandora.
The umbilical cord is gone.
Oxygen uptake: 89.
In case you were in any doubt,
you are Colonel Miles Quaritch, -
- just younger, taller,
bluer and less pretty.
In two hours I will
attack the Na'vi fortress.
It was thought advisable
that I make this backup.
And if you see it, it means
I've put the clogs away.
Parker, what the
hell else can I say?
Just remind him how it works.
Your memories and your personality
are sent back to Earth, -
- where you are being cultivated.
You will have them instilled…
Is it me or you doing this?
The idea is to transfer the psyche from
the toughest extraterrestrial actors -
- as Corporal Wainfleet
there and signed -
- til recombinant body.
You are a recombinant souled
with my memories and my charm.
You won't be able to remember my
death because it hasn't happened yet.
And it won't come
to that either.
Whatever happened, you as a clone
of me will thirst for revenge, -
- primarily over Jake Sully.
Remember that a Marine
can never be defeated.
You can kill us, but
we'll regroup in hell.
Semper fi.
Land force, now!
Day ago!
Two minutes, guys.
- We have to go down there, bro.
- Father will kill us.
Now don't be such a douchebag.
Lo'ak, come back!
The entire box must be included,
both magazines and rocket guides.
- Come on bro! - Lo'ak!
Take it. Take a weapon, kid.
Lo'ak, you don't even
know how to use it.
Dad showed me that.
A helicopter gunship!
Come on bro!
Lo'ak, where are you? Netay!
Are you unharmed?
where is your brother
- Over there. - Hurry away!
Not finished!
Oh no.
Far?
What the hell were
you doing here?
Pardon.
Sorry, Dad.
We're not in Kansas anymore.
We're on our way to Pandora.
I know you are all asking
yourselves the same question:
Is it blue monday?
The sins of the past have made us
reborn in the form of our enemies.
We have their size, their
strength, their speed.
Added to our training,
it's a powerful cocktail.
- Have we got a mission?
- We have that.
Our mission is to find and kill
the leader of the na'vi rebel army.
Him they call "toruk makto".
Jake Sully.
Attack, attack! Got you!
Come on now, Tuk.
I'm clearly faster when I'm blue.
And the animals show me more respect.
- They don't see me as a person.
- Wait, are you human?
They are coming!
THE FORTRESS OF THE OMATIKAYAS
They come! Kiri! Spider!
The warriors have
returned! Came!
Come along.
- Mor! - Tuck, Tuck, Tuck.
Step up.
You are scouts. You must keep an
eye out for enemies. At a distance!
Does that sound familiar? Here I let
you fly a mission and then you disobey.
- Kiri, help with the wounded.
- My brother is also injured.
- Tuk, go with her.
- Father, I take full responsibility.
Yes, because you are the oldest
and you must behave accordingly.
- MaJake, your son is bleeding.
- It doesn't matter, mother.
Go in and get patched up.
You must be aware that you
almost had your brother killed.
You are banned from
flying for a month.
Look at the Ukrainians. All of them.
And wipe the nastiness off your face.
- Should I breathe on it?
- Give him this.
- I would use yalnabark.
- Aha. Who is tsahik here?
You are, grandma, but
yalnabark is better.
- It hurts less.
- Mighty warriors.
What is it?
Neteyam and Lo'ak try
to live up to you.
It's hard for them.
I know.
You are hard on them.
I am their father.
That's my job.
We are not a platoon.
We are a family.
I thought we had lost him.
- Hi there. - Hey, Spider.
- I'll knock you out.
- Just come.
Only avatars are allowed
here. Walk around.
- The blue stripes don't make you bigger.
- I can still spread you out.
- What a day. - It was long.
Very funny. It is so clean down there
that you can breathe earth air for hours.
I can only inhale
yours for ten seconds.
Yes, it's downright,
monkey cat. For you.
- Hey, Max. - Hey, kids.
Hi Mom.
Maybe I'm getting cocky,
but I see real evidence -
- on a systemic response
at global level.
I can not...
I will not use the
word "intelligence".
"Awareness" is
probably a better word.
It's as if the entire
biosphere on Pandora -
- is conscious and able
to respond cognitively.
I can't say that.
Then they crucify me.
Who do you think did her roe?
- It was guaranteed Norm.
- Definitely.
- You don't deserve to live.
- Think about it.
He is with her constantly.
I wanted to commit suicide.
I wanted to drink acid.
He is in all recordings. Look
at the look he gives her.
I imagine their avatars
together out in the woods…
Ad!
It's not always cool to
know who your father was.
Hole in it. I don't
even remember him.
No, Spider...
Spider...
You are not him.
BRIDGEHEAD CITY
Inside the terminal!
No stay! Go!
Masks off.
Colonel, it's the general.
General Ardmore.
Nice to meet you, Colonel.
I hear good things.
But a lot has changed since
you were here last. Came.
The new command center here
has just been commissioned.
The crowd fitters can erect
a building in six days.
We have done more here in one year
than in the previous 30 years.
We are not here to run a mine. I
have a far more important mission.
The earth is dying.
Our task is to tame
the wilderness -
- with the aim of making Pandora
the new home of humanity.
But before we can do that, we
have to pacify the savages.
Sully's whims have become
bolder and more frequent.
His attacks are well executed. There is
good coordination between the troops.
They go after mines and pipelines
and sabotage our supply chain.
They attacked a mag
train two days ago.
- Do we know anything about Sully's base?
- Yes. Show me the mountains.
There is a cave system in
the Hallelujah Mountains.
But every time we send troops
up there, we suffer losses.
It's like poking a wasp's nest.
After ten minutes in their
airspace they swarm around us.
Colonel, we think your blue team
will be mistaken for natives -
- and not trigger
an immune reaction.
How do we test that hypothesis?
The hard way.
Wonderful.
- We are approaching enemy airspace.
- Received.
- Come on, monkey!
- Wait for me!
- Tuk, come on. - Okay, okay.
Why did you bring her?
The honking princess. "I'm gossiping.
You must not go out to the battlefield.
I'll tell mother if
you don't take me."
Come on.
- How crazy! - Is there a body?
Hold that up.
Kiri? Kiri.
Kiri. Kiri...
- Are you okay?
- I did it again, didn't I?
Yes, you did.
Skin!
- We have to see to come back.
- Came.
What is it?
We must be home before dark.
- Too big to be human.
- Avatars?
Maybe, but not any of ours.
- What are you doing?
- Following the tracks.
Keep your back covered.
Secured.
Make a call.
Holy shit.
We shouldn't be here at all.
Dad gives you a no-fly zone
for the rest of your life.
We have to look into it.
Bro, that's where your
father and my father fought.
- It's your father's suit.
- Holy shit...
Lyle, check for
data on the camera.
- It's stone dead, Colonel.
- We were too.
- I have to report this.
- We get so much trouble.
- They will Dog, it's Eagle Eye.
- Eagle Eye, come forward.
I've spotted someone.
They look like avatars, -
- but they wear camouflage and
assault rifles. There are six of them.
What is your position?
We are at the old cabin.
Who are we"?
Me, Spider, Kiri...
and Tuk.
Now you are listening very
well. Retreat silently.
- Hurry out of there. Understood?
- Yes. We are on the way.
Dad, I know a loophole.
- You get into so much trouble.
- Now stop, Kiri.
It's eclipse right away.
- Put it down or I'll shoot!
- Come with me.
- Drop it! - Right now!
Put it, put it.
Come here! Down on your
knees! Stop bragging.
- Visit them for weapons.
- Kiri!
Take it easy.
Shut up!
What do we have here?
Look, Colonel. Four
fingers. It's a half-breed.
Show me your fingers.
You're his, aren't you?
Yes, you are his.
Where is he?
Unfortunately I
don't speak English -
- with assholes.
Where is your father?
Should it be with it on?
Shut up!
- Kiri! No, don't!
- You don't touch her!
You mustn't hurt her.
- Stand still.
- What's your name, kid?
Spider Socorro.
Miles?
Nobody calls me that.
It was hell. I assumed you
had been sent back to Earth.
Children cannot
tolerate cryo, clap hat.
What do we do, boss?
Iron Sky, Blue 1 here.
- Blue 1, come forward.
- We are ready for collection.
- Fly us in.
- Dragonfly begins collection.
We bring very
valuable prisoners.
- Blue 1, we're on our way.
- Arrival in ten.
We're counting down.
Lyle, get me sound on this one.
- It's Sully's wife.
- She's a wild animal.
Giv op, Quaritch.
- Sully. - Stupid pig.
It's not over as long
as I'm breathing.
I was hoping you would say that.
- You stay with the Iranians.
- But I'm a warrior like you.
I won't say it again.
Bleach.
There is no more after that.
Should we salvage the remains?
Blue 1, we'll be there
in three minutes.
Three minutes.
Cover our backs.
Shut up!
Then clap in!
Skirmish in the rear!
Lo'ak!
You little shit!
- Tuck, come on! - Race!
Come along!
In cover!
Come now!
Is that you, Mrs. Sully? I
recognize your business card.
Come forward freely, Mrs. Sully. The
two of us have an unfinished business.
Demon! I will kill you as
many times as it takes.
You and the corporal have been
really diligent, haven't you?
You have raised a
litter of half-breeds.
After' four!
Run, run, run!
Are you okay, kid?
Follow me. Clear?
Not!
Come on!
- Run, run, run! - After them!
Spider?
- Spider! - Kiri!
Come here!
Spider is down there!
- Then we are ahead. We have ten minutes.
- Blue 1, back to the collection point.
- Blue 1, fall back. - Back!
Back, back! Take off!
Kiri, come on! Come on!
Run, run, run!
- Are you hurt? - No, I'm fine.
Tuk, are you hurt?
Then the danger is over.
Is everyone unharmed?
Tuk!
We made it.
Thank you, All
courage is, thank you.
Where is Spider?
They took him. They took him.
Take it easy, honey.
He's a cool kid.
He'll probably make it.
We'll probably make
it all together.
Before hell!
Let me out!
He has become like a savage.
He thinks he is one of them.
The Quaritch creature can wade in
here without Eywa spotting him.
- Our home is here.
- This applies to our children.
You can't ask me for that.
I cannot leave my
people. I will not.
He's chasing us. He's
after our family.
You can't ask me for that. The children
only know the forest. Our home is here!
He had our children. He
had them under his knife.
My father gave me the bow
here when he was dying.
He told me to protect the
people. You are toruk makto!
This will protect the people. Quaritch
has Spider and he knows everything.
He can lead them right here.
If the people hide us,
they will be killed.
Do you understand that?
I have nothing. I
don't have any plan.
But I can protect our family.
One thing I know.
Wherever we are,
family is our fortress.
- Where's Jake Sully?
- I do not know!
- We know, you know.
Form a picture in your mind. Does
it represent the floating mountains?
- Release me!
- He bristles against.
Dan a thought, and we'll see.
- I do not know!
- I don't enjoy this either.
- Which clans protect him?
- I have no idea!
The forehead patch
goes absolutely crazy.
It won't stop until you
tell us where he is.
I don't know, you assholes!
Let me try the personal angle.
He is not your son.
Funny, Tarzan, funny.
Are you calm?
You're cool, kid. The researchers
gave you the rough file, -
- but you didn't
reveal anything.
I respect that.
Maybe you want this.
This is Colonel Miles
Quaritch. Deceased.
The decline in service.
I'm not him.
But I have his memories.
And they tell me, -
- that he wasn't the
world's best father.
But that is not an excuse.
I'm not your father. Technically,
the two of us are not related.
But I can help you. I
can get you out of here.
I won't ask you to betray Jake Sully.
You would never do that. You are loyal.
And I admire loyalty.
Now just take it.
Otherwise I must leave
you to the coattails.
My heart is heavy as stone.
Tarsem is young but wise. He
will become a strong olo'eyktan.
The leader must die...
so that the leader can be born.
Toruk makto will disappear.
The people will be
able to know for sure.
A father protects. That
is his purpose in life.
One life ends.
Another begins.
Oh, Tuk...
The sea clans inhabit a world of
their own. Thousands of islands.
An unknown area where we will be
able to disappear without a trace.
Aren't we there soon?
AWA'ATLU, IN METKAYINA-LANDSBY
Let it stay.
Follow me.
Tuk.
Behave nicely.
Take it easy.
What is it? Should
it represent a tail?
It is then too
small to swim with.
Hang on, Rotxo and Ao'nung.
Hi.
Tonowari was chief of the
Metkayina, the reef people.
- I see you, Tonowari.
- Jake Sully.
He was known as a harsh leader.
But it wasn't Tonowari
that worried me.
I see you, Ron al, the
tsahik of the metkayinas.
I see you, Ron al.
- What do you want from us, Jake Sully?
- We are looking for a trip...
- Uturu? - Asylum for my family.
We are reef people. You are forest
people. Your skills cannot be used here.
So we want to get to
know yours, right?
Their arms are thin.
Their tails are weak. You
will be slow in the water.
The kids aren't even true Na'vi.
Yes, we are.
There is demon blood in them!
Se her.
I was born of the sky people and
now I am na'vi. You can adapt.
We will adapt.
My husband was toruk makto.
He led the clans to victory
over the Sky People.
Do you call it a victory
to hide among strangers?
Eywa has apparently turned her
back on you, you chosen one.
You must bear with my mate. She has
flown a long way and is exhausted.
Toruk makto is a mighty war
hero. All Na'vi know his story.
But we Metkayina are not at war.
We can't let you
take the war here.
I'm done with war, okay?
I just want to
protect my family.
We have asked for an outing...
- Will we be sent away?
- It will be OK.
Toruk makto and his
family stay with us.
Consider them our brothers and
sisters. But they don't know the sea.
Therefore, they will be like
newborns taking their first breath.
Teach them about our way of life so that they
will not suffer the shame of being useless.
- What do you say then?
- Thanks.
So.
My son Ao'nung and daughter
Tsireya will guide your children.
- Why? - It has been decided.
Come and see our village.
This way.
Come on now, Tuk.
It's right up here.
This is your new home.
It's possible.
That's cool, huh?
- Sully is, step up.
- There is a family meeting.
- Down on your knees. - Kiri.
What?
I need you to behave in an
exemplary manner. I mean it.
Learn quickly, take your turn, and
avoid making trouble. Understood?
Bleach.
I want to go home.
Oh, Tuk...
Tuk, this is our home now.
We'll probably make it.
- As long as we look after each other.
- What is it that dad always says?
Sully is a stickler.
Yes, Sully is a stickler.
Then say it with conviction.
- Sully is a stickler.
Come on!
Swim with us.
- What's wrong with them?
- They are bad at diving.
Stop. They just
have to learn it.
- Are you okay?
- You swim far too fast.
Just breathe.
You are not good at diving. You are
probably better at swinging in the trees.
- Stop it.
- We don't understand your sign language.
- I'll probably teach you that.
- Where has Kiri gone?
- Where is she?
- Have you seen her?
Hop on board, find a seat,
and don't get in the way.
- Come on, hurry up! - Coolest.
Stop halfway, Karl Smart.
Listen. There is a transmitter
built into the mask.
If you run away, I'll catch
you at zero point five -
- and gives you an old-fashioned
finish. Understood?
- Understood? - Yes.
- Clear? - All clear.
Listen carefully. Jake
Sully has gone underground.
But we'll probably find
him and his crazy madame.
To be able to do that,
we must be na'vi.
Too full screw.
We must eat like the Na'vi, ride like
the Na'vi and think like the Na'vi.
And first of all,
we must speak Na'vi.
Do you call that speaking na'vi?
You sound like a three year old.
Okay, klogeåge.
You've just been promoted from our
monkey mascot to our interpreter.
It's an illusion. If you want to
live here, you must be able to ride.
Tie the ribbon carefully.
Feel his breath.
Feel his strength.
Hold fast her.
- Look at his legs.
- Hold tight.
Everything okay, wood goblin?
This warwalker is difficult to master.
Maybe you should start with an il...
No, this one.
Remember, when diving, it is
important to take the right position.
I can do it.
Yes like that.
Calm.
I love her already.
Breathe in…
and exhale.
Imagine breathing into a flame.
You must say your heartbeat.
Breathe in.
Breathe all the way down here.
And exhale slowly.
Lo'ak, your heart beats
fast. Try to concentrate.
Breathe in…
and exhale. Empty your mind.
You are learning to breathe.
Come on, losers!
Let me.
What is it?
Na'vi children do this
with their bare fists.
- Did Sully do it the hard way?
- What do you think?
What do we do?
This is going to be good.
Forward.
It's you and me, baby.
Did I say you have to tie
the beak together first?
Ih, tak!
Forward!
Can you see them?
Come on, we have to move on.
Take off.
Yes, because!
That's right, Colonel!
Whose turn is it then?
The being of water has
no beginning and no end.
The sea is around
you and in you.
The sea is your home
before your birth...
and after your death.
Our hearts beat in
the lap of the world.
Our breath burns in the
shadows of the deep.
The sea gives and the sea takes.
Water ties everything together.
Life and death.
The dark and the light.
- I got it! Tsireya!
- You did it.
They let us breathe underwater.
What is she doing?
- Have no idea.
- She just stares at the sand.
What did you say?
Are you a form of deformity?
Are you a deformity?
No.
Are you sure? You
are not a real na'vi.
Look at those hands. See.
Skrid, fish face.
- Another four-fingered deformity.
- Look at his little baby tail.
- Let us be! - He's not normal.
Look at his tail.
It is very cute.
You heard her. Leave them alone.
Big Brother...
Step with you. Now.
Sensible. And from now on,
please respect my sister.
Come on.
Farewell!
They are deformities,
the whole family.
- Lo'ak... - Calm down bro.
Yes, my hand is weird.
I am a deformity.
But it can do something cool.
First I tie it really tight.
And then…
It's called a stroke, weakling. You
will never touch my sister again.
Hold on!
Stop it!
That's too stupid!
Off, my tail!
My ear! Let it go!
He rips my ear!
- What had I asked you?
- To avoid making trouble.
- It was my fault.
- You must not take out the rubbish for him.
Ao'nung called Kiri a deformity.
Say sorry to Ao'nung.
He is the chief's son.
I don't care how, as long
as you make peace with him.
- What did the others look like?
- Worse.
- Well. - Much worse.
Go away.
What's wrong?
Nothing. I'm fine.
Why shouldn't I?
Why can't I just be
like everyone else?
Skin...
What is the tree
runner doing here?
Sorry, I hit you a
whole bunch of times.
Let's be friends.
Join us on a hunt outside the
reef. This is where the men hunt.
- I must not.
- I asked the wrong brother.
Let's do it.
Come on!
Stay tuned, forest troll!
THE WOODEN BREAD CUTTERS
- You survived.
- It was awesome!
Come on, I know a good place.
Cold on the fish.
What a fool.
Gutter?
Yes!
It's not funny!
Holy shit.
You are a tulkun.
You saved my life. Thanks.
So.
I have no idea what you said.
They have done you harm.
I try to pull it out.
Trust me.
Friends?
Yes, we are friends.
Bro!
I am sorry.
What's the matter, honey?
Do you miss Spider?
Yes, but it's not.
Okay. What is it then?
I can feel her, Dad.
- Mark who? - Eywa.
I can hear her breathing.
I can hear her heartbeat.
She is so close.
She is present...
like a word that is
right on the tongue.
I know you think I'm crazy.
You're not crazy, honey.
So what does Eywa's
heartbeat sound like?
Powerful.
Tell him what you told me.
Do you like stargazing?
My father came from a star.
The one right there.
- Lo'ak! - Now I'm on it.
We will meet again.
- The boy has been found!
- The Sully boy has been found!
Let me see you.
He is unharmed. It's
just a few scratches.
Give me strength not to
tear my eyes out at my son.
No. My son knew not to
take him outside the reef.
The fault is his.
Come on.
No. It's not Ao'nung's
fault. It was my idea.
Ao'nung actually tried
to talk me out of it.
- Lo'ak. - Pardon.
Come on.
I will probably.
- Is it true?
- What were you thinking?
You yourself said I should
be friends with them.
I don't want to hear about it. You
have brought shame on the family.
- Can I leave now?
- Next time I'll tie a knot in your tail.
- Is that understood?
- Yes. Lima Charlie.
- Where were you?
- You should keep an eye on your brother.
Pardon.
Why did you speak for me?
Because I know what it's like
to be one big disappointment.
Wish I had been there.
The sea gave you a gift.
The tulkuns have not come yet,
and no tulkun swims alone.
It did here.
He was missing his one fin.
The left one was only a stump.
Payakan. Det er Payakan.
- Who is Payakan?
- A young, unruly bull.
He is outcast and missing a fin.
- He was supposed to be a killer.
- He has killed Na'vi and Tulkuns.
- Far down south.
- He's not a killer.
- You're lucky you survived.
- Well, he saved my life.
- He is my friend.
- My little brother...
The mighty warrior who fought
a killer tulkun and survived.
You don't listen.
- I'm listening.
- Lo'ak, come back.
Payakan!
Good to see you.
Why are you outcast?
What happened?
It's too painful.
I trust you. You can trust me.
Oh, that's lame.
Faster!
So here we are.
The Vig of the Ancestors
is our holiest place.
Eclipse is the best
time to be here.
There it is. The Spirit Tree.
My pretty daughter.
Hi Mom.
It's nice to see you.
But you look worried.
Sweetie, it'll be fine.
- What's wrong?
- Why am I different?
What does the Almother want me?
Who was my father?
Oh, my own…
- Come now! - Kiri!
Skin!
- What's wrong?
- She had a seizure.
Is she breathing?
- Get her home to the village.
- Lets go!
- Good to see you.
- Neteyam, keep them away.
- How is she?
- Still unconscious.
No bleeding, no breakage.
The lack of oxygen has
not damaged the brain.
But there is interictal
activity in the frontal lobe.
She must have had a seizure.
We can rule out toxins.
- I'm not needed here.
- You are tsahik.
- Remove the remedies.
- Out! You have done nothing!
- Come on, we're taking a break.
- Let me just take the drop out.
Tuktirey.
She said she could feel
Eywa and hear her heartbeat.
- It is typical frontal lobe epilepsy.
- Epilepsy?
One sees visions and experiences religious
ecstasy like the one she described.
The association with the Spirit
Tree must have triggered it.
Don't let her do that again.
Never?
Jake, if she has another seizure
underwater, she could die.
Kiri, you are awake.
Kiri, sweet child.
My lovely girl.
Try this one: "I see you."
I said that too.
I don't know. Ngaati.
Okay, it's going out
through the nose.
Chief, one of the patrols has detected
a helicopter gunship on the radar.
- Where?
- Above the sea, 400 km to the north.
Hold fast.
The signal disappeared
out over the open sea.
But if you continue the course,
you will hit this archipelago.
There are hundreds of islands
with countless villages.
It's him. Give me some vessels and
I will return home with his scalp.
- We will be flown in.
- Skipper.
- Stop the engines. - Yes.
Are you Scoresby?
Are you the badass
taking my ship?
It is me.
The target is the
entire archipelago.
I've never been up there. You
know the waters. Who lives there?
Primarily metkayinas,
about 50 villages.
Who are you?
Ian Garvin, marinbiolog.
If there are 100 villages,
we search them all.
I hunt tulkuns. That's what
we do. I have quotas to meet.
I'm being polite the first
time. Then it's over.
If you can't avoid
it, get into it.
- All men at their posts!
- Hello, no pills.
- Rudder threads, airspeed.
- Yes.
- What was it?
- What's going on?
The Tulkuns have returned! Our
brothers and sisters are back!
Their endless cycle of wandering
had brought the Tulkuns home.
Skin!
- Kiri, come!
- Tuk, leave me alone.
- What is it you want? - Look!
Let's go out and meet them.
There is my soul sister.
Sister, I see you.
I see you and I am happy.
Your son is very handsome.
Thanks. How is your little one?
My little one is strong.
I have met a boy.
Now stories had to be told about
the time they had been apart.
About death and births.
About old friends and new love.
TA'UNUI-LANDSBY
Keep calm.
We are looking for weapons,
radios, technical equipment.
Down on your knees!
Can you see it here?
Shut up!
We know this man resides somewhere
here on the islands. Is he here?
Our tribe lives in seclusion. The man
in the picture is from the forest.
- What is he saying?
- That forest people never come here.
I don't buy it.
He must search in the forest
if he is to find that man.
They know nothing.
Shoot that animal.
What are you doing?
Take it easy.
Are your ears working now? Now
you have seen what they can do.
Jake Sully. Toruk makto!
He knows nothing.
Kill her.
Stop! Stop!
Cut it out of cardboard for him. If he
doesn't expose Sully, we'll kill the tsahik.
No, I refuse. I don't
want to be part of this.
They know nothing!
Are we really going to kill her?
You must not do that. What you
are doing here is so wrong!
Do not.
- Burn the cabins.
- Set them on fire.
Set fire to it all!
- Forgive me. I did not know it.
- You must stop the madness!
- Forgive me. - We have slipped.
Don't touch me!
Come on. Sit up!
- What's wrong? - Sky people.
They're looking for you down south. They
have a human boy with them who speaks Na'vi.
- Have they killed anyone?
- Not yet.
They threaten to, but no one will
reveal where you are. On my command.
We must hunt this demon.
Catch him and kill him.
We have to think about it.
If we attack Quaritch, they will
follow us here with their full force.
So what do we do?
We are looking for toruk
makto! Has he been here?
- It is no use.
- They are silent as the grave.
If we continue, he'll just run
away. We have to lure him out.
I'm done. I have quotas to meet.
Do you want to
hunt? Then we hunt.
Well not here? There are
too many villages here.
No no no.
They do not understand the bond
of community between the Tulkuns -
- and the Havna'vi. It would
be like murdering their family.
If we hunt here, the
savages will come after us.
Exactly. One definitely wild.
I know how you feel.
I also feel completely alone.
Tell me. Why were you expelled?
I am sorry. It
hurts me terribly.
It is okay.
You allowed it.
You allowed him to
bond with the outcast.
Tsireya... You
disappoint me, daughter.
And you are the son of a great warrior.
You are better raised than that.
Payakan saved my life.
They don't know him.
Sit.
Sit down!
Hear my words, boy.
In the time of the first songs, the
tulkuns fought among themselves -
- to gain territory
and to get revenge.
But they realized that
killing, justified or not, -
- just leads to more killing.
Therefore, it was
forbidden to kill.
It is the way of
life of the tulkuns.
Payakan is a killer and
therefore he is an outcast.
- Sorry, but you are wrong.
- Lo'ak, you are speaking to the olo'eyktan.
- Well... - That's good!
I know what I know.
Then it's good.
I'll take care of him.
The storm will
probably blow over.
Lo'ak, I saw something today.
I saw a forest boy
selected by a tulkun.
I am very proud of you.
It was not Payakan who
killed the boys. I saw it.
The demon ship killed his mother,
so he gathered the young bulls -
- and the reef boys to attack the
ship, and they were all killed.
But of the people of heaven,
not of him. He's not a killer.
According to the law of the Tulkuns,
he is responsible for their death.
Will he have to pay for it for the rest of
his life? He knows what he did was wrong.
- We have to tell my father...
- No. My father is furious.
- Your father will understand.
- No. He doesn't understand anything.
The whole clan hates me. Demon
blood, stranger. That's all they see.
I see you.
You are the brother of a tulkun.
You are one of us now.
- Have you found the mother?
- And the calf. 4000 meters.
- Hull in the water!
- Yes. Carrier plan activated.
Submarine teams, two minutes!
Close the hatches! Hurry up!
Crews to their boats!
Let's earn some dates.
Folks, get off the ropes!
The boats in the water!
Go!
Take off!
Depth charges ready.
Guy, guy, guy!
What are they doing?
There are echolocation sensors,
with which they navigate.
They keep them afloat
so they don't go deaf.
Picadors, away with you!
They isolate the cow from the
herd using the sound cannon.
They go after the mother because the
calf is slow and she won't leave it.
- Do they ever resist?
- No, they never lift a fin.
But they are some sailing
devils. Submarine teams, go!
Disconnection.
- There we have the lady.
- Target in sight. Harpoons ready.
Then we go to it.
We attack from below, where
their armor has cracks.
- Okay, that's it now.
- Get me really close.
- Hold it steady.
- Arm the eater.
- Armed. - Fires the eater.
2 ready. Arm the eater. Guy!
- Perfect match.
- Fires the deuce.
- Cookie!
- 3-6, you owe a bajer.
The bags sink her and pull
her up towards the surface.
Bring me closer! Very
close. 30 meters.
Granatharpun.
10 meters. Get me
all the way in there.
Keep the boat
steady! Wait, wait.
The line runs!
Keep your hat and ponytail on.
- Full power back! - Yes.
Hold her!
She got a grenade harpoon in the chest,
but she keeps swimming. Beautiful.
We can only get to the gland from below,
so we drill up through the palate -
- and into the brain.
They are highly intelligent.
Probably smarter than us.
- Not smarter than me.
- Then the bar is set low.
I'm the one with the harpoon.
And yes.
- How do you know they are smarter than us?
- They have more neurons and nerve fibers.
They are not only smarter,
but also deeply emotional.
More spiritual.
The area here corresponds
to our emotional center, -
- but is proportionally
much larger.
They have music,
philosophy, mathematics -
- and a complex language.
- Okay, that's it now.
- Bring on the horrors.
- So it's the hops?
- In fact. Amrita.
Unfortunately for them,
dirt can stop human aging.
Completely.
The most valuable raw
material known to mankind.
This small container is worth
approximately 80 million.
Wants!
Do not do that.
It's never funny.
Amrita funds everything
here on Pandora now.
- Even your research, Dr. G.
- That's why I drink.
Don't you take anything else?
Does the rest just go to waste?
Empty the bags and let her sink.
No, leave the bags alone.
They need to know it was us.
I need extra payment
to act as bait.
Her name is Ro'a.
She was my soul sister.
She composed songs.
She was highly regarded.
We sang together.
She waited many breeding cycles to
have a calf. The clan cheered for her.
What's going on, Tonowari?
What happens?
My spirit sister and her child have
been murdered by the sky people.
The war has come to us. We knew that
our tulkun family was being hunted, -
- but it happened far from
here. Now this is happening!
You have to understand
how the sky people think.
- They don't care about the balance of life.
- They can run us!
Now listen to him.
This is just the beginning.
Tell the Tulkuns to flee.
Say they must flee far away.
Escape?
You have lived among us, but
you have learned nothing.
We will fight for our
brothers and sisters!
No no no.
If you attack them,
they will wipe you out.
They will wipe out
everything you hold dear.
Hear my words! Hear my words!
Keep calm!
Now listen to my father.
He speaks the truth.
Tell the tulkuns, -
- that if they are hit by such a
person, they are designated to die.
Summon me and I'll silence it.
Saving their lives is the only
thing that matters, right?
To save your family.
Notify the interpreters.
Off, off.
We must take up the fight.
MaJake... I won't just stand by.
They just want us to strike again. They
don't hunt tulkuns. They are hunting us.
- You're not going anywhere, little brother.
- I have to warn Payakan.
Zero. You stay here, skxawng.
He is an outcast. No
one else will warn him.
Bro, why do you have to make
everything so difficult?
You mean why can't I be perfect
like you? The perfect soldier.
I'm not you, okay?
I'm not you. He's
my brother. I do it.
Is he your brother?
No, I'm your brother.
Lo'ak!
Let go of me.
Lo'ak! He wants
to go to Payakan.
Come back!
- The er Lo'ak. - Loak!
- He wants to find Payakan.
- Wait for us.
Hold fast.
All men at their posts. Come,
there's money to be made!
Payakan! Brother!
Lo'ak!
- Lo'ak! - Twenty!
What's wrong?
Shit!
Take it easy. I remove it.
Lo'ak!
Bro, help me! The
ship is approaching!
Come now!
Come on bro.
Summon father! Just do it!
- Just do it!
- They will However, can you hear me?
- Did you see where they went?
- Outside the reef.
- Lo'ak? - Far!
We are with a tulkun who
is attacked by a ship.
- It is 2 km away.
- Who is with you?
All of us, at the
Three Brothers Cliffs.
Hide and do not attack. Is that
understood? We are on the way.
- Oh well.
- It's getting closer!
Pull!
The children are attacked. They defend
a tulkun. Your children are there too.
- Dæmonskibet? - Yes!
To arms! Sound the alarm!
- You better stay.
- I'm riding along!
Submarines, close the
hatches! Two minutes!
- Ao'nung! - Hurry up bro!
Quickly!
Pull over!
All at the same time!
It was hell. Sully's kids.
- Take off. Not you. - Sit up!
700 meters. The signal is clear.
- Pull up! - Pull!
- It came out! - Go, Tuk.
Off with you! The
path! I lure them away!
Payakan, dyk!
Tuk, hold fast.
- 300 meters.
- Depth charges ready.
Short, short, short!
No bombs. The kids are worth
nothing if they are dead.
The fire on hold.
Circle them. Launch
the submarines.
Submarines in the tub!
Crabs, turn right.
- They must not get away.
- The wings in!
Such!
Fires the deuce.
Where is Tuk?
Tuk!
Target in sight.
- It is coming! - We have to go.
Change network. Guy.
Hang on!
- Beware! Move your hand!
- Hurry up!
Come back!
- Drop your weapon! - Put it!
Stay there.
Come here, kid!
Put down your weapon!
- Put it! - Drop the knife!
Hello, stop! You
must not harm them!
Lie still!
- Bro, are you okay?
- I have never felt better.
Go back on the bridge.
Make sure he stays there!
I'm on my way.
I remember you well.
Chain them to the railing.
Come on!
- Be careful, they bite.
- Down on your knees.
Come with your hand.
And then the other.
Be brave.
After' four!
- Hang on! - Left flank!
Stop! Stop dem!
It's Sully.
300 meter.
They have our children.
Your daughter, Tuk, Lo'ak...
Jake, tell your
friends to back off.
If you want your children,
you will come forward alone.
You know not to
doubt my coolness.
I took you under my wing,
Jake, and you betrayed me.
You killed your comrades. I will
not hesitate to execute your son.
Now wait a bit.
Stay here.
They are interpreter killers.
They must die. Here, today.
They are only after me. That's why they
hunted down the Tulkuns and took our children.
This is your fault! Your!
Therefore, it is I
who must do this.
Offer expires soon.
What will it be?
Stop shooting. I am coming.
MaJake, what's going on?
MaJake?
Be alert, everyone.
- Straight to the point.
- If you shoot now, they will attack.
Wait until he's on board.
Payakan!
Shoot! Shoot!
Broder!
Do around! Turn me around!
Get me on fire! Now, now!
Out, quick!
Get me on fire!
Because!
Holy shit!
Give fire! Give fire!
Sully approaches.
Keep an eye on him.
Come on, sit up!
So shoot something!
Stop!
After them!
Leak! Masks on!
Get him out!
Hurry up!
- Damage report?
- Rooms 2 and 3 are under water.
Are you ok
- Port for the bow!
- Hard to port!
Get me on fire!
Now I have you!
- Get us free!
- It doesn't react.
- Cut the cable!
- Who has the harpoon now?
Full power behind!
Let the harpoon!
No cable, you idiot!
We are wrecked.
- We take in water.
- Man your weapons!
- Otherwise, I thought you were so clever.
- Close the food gap, Garvin.
Where did you go,
you cunning satan?
You probably think
you're cunning, huh?
Because!
- The pumps don't work.
- All men aboard!
Get him on board a
boat! Hurry up, guys!
- Neteyam!
- Do you need help, little brother?
Now clap in and cut us free.
- Get Tuk out of here.
- Hurry up!
Who is the mighty warrior?
Say it. Let's get away.
Lo'ak!
They have Spider. We have to save
him. Come on, we can't let him down.
Let go of me!
No!
Se!
- Up with you, baby.
- I'm not your cunt, you pig.
- We have to save her.
- Tuck, wait!
Sully is a stickler.
Wait, wait! Ready for departure!
- Tighten the mask.
- Leave me alone.
Hurry up! There
is an evacuation!
Tuk, this is not a good idea.
Cut here. Come on.
I have her.
We can still make it.
Now I'm tied up again!
- Come on bro. - Off.
Thanks, boys.
Race! Come on bro!
Run, run, run!
Give me that.
- Run, run, run! - This way!
In cover!
Can I say them?
Bro, that was too crazy.
- Hop on! - Come now.
Your skxawng. I am wounded.
Shit! Give me a hand!
- Hold him up! - I have him.
- Take him. - I have him.
- Holy shit. - Hold him up!
Come on bro.
- I have you. - Hurry up!
They have Kiri and Tuk.
I can't turn around.
Sheep! Help! It's Neteyam!
- Quick! - Take him.
Neteyam is hurt! Hurry up!
Pull!
Careful with his head.
Come now!
- Don't worry, bro, we've got you.
- Oh no.
Press down on it.
- Dad... - I'm here.
I'm with you, my boy.
I want to go home.
I know. We should
probably go home.
- It will probably work.
- Father...
Incomplete?
No no no...
Not finished!
Netay! No, All courage is...
My son! My son!
My son!
Can you hear me, Corporal?
I think you can.
I have your daughters.
Same offer as before.
You for them.
Where are your sisters
Where are they?
- I do not know.
- They are trapped on board the ship.
They are at the moonpool.
On the well deck, amidships.
Come, I'll show you.
Answer me, Corporal. Spit it out
or there will be consequences.
I have heard you.
Come on, we have to go. Come on.
Listen to me. Listen to me.
Listen to me. They
have our daughters.
They have our daughters.
I need you to be with me
and I need you to be strong.
Right now. Strong of heart.
Strong of heart.
Now we save our daughters.
- Stay with your brother.
- I want to go with you.
- You have done enough.
- Sheep...
The fire on hold.
Come on.
He's on his way.
Swim!
Now we neck him.
That's why we're here.
- Stay with him. - No!
Be careful, guys.
Not.
- Where are they?
- On the submarine deck.
There is a well in the middle.
They are at the railing.
No, stay here.
Talk to me, Corporal. The ship is sinking
and your girls are going down with it.
Your son didn't have to
die. It was your own fault.
You thought you could protect
your family, but you can't.
There is only one solution.
Now let's get this over with
before you lose another youngster.
In cover!
- Who is affected? - Zdinarsik?
Secured.
Prague, are you there?
Look up!
Forward!
To the left!
To the right. Surround her.
MaJake!
It's mother!
They come to kill you.
Far!
- Where is your sister?
- The path.
Stay behind me.
Skin!
Time is running out, Corporal.
Do you really want to
lose another youngster?
You shall not try!
Just kill him, dad!
Skin!
- Put down your weapons.
- You must not do that!
Kick them away.
Do it!
No...
- Put on handcuffs.
- Leave her alone.
Stay there! Don't
come one step closer.
- Handcuffs on!
- You stupid pig.
You mustn't do anything to her.
Let go or I'll cut.
What does the kid do to me?
He is not mine. We are
not even the same species.
You mustn't hurt
her. Let her go.
Now listen to me. Let her go.
- Mother, you must not kill him.
- A son for a son.
You mustn't hurt her.
- I cut. - Now just let her go.
No!
Kiri, Kiri...
- Spider!
- Get them out of here.
- Come with me.
- I owe you a death.
Mom, come on. Mother!
You're not vaporizing, are you,
Jake? You know I never give up.
I will come and kill
your whole family.
Far!
Come on.
Jake!
- The fire is coming!
- Back to the ship!
Stay close to me.
Tuk!
Mother, take my hand!
Mor!
Come on, Kiri, we have
to get out of here.
Climb up!
Come on, Kiri. Race!
Swim! Climb up, Tuk!
Race!
- Mother! - Run, run, run!
Crawl on!
I have you.
Give me your hand!
Open it up!
- Open it up! - Back, back!
Come on!
Tuk!
Up! Come on.
Crawl! Get up!
We're guessing! Further!
Kiri, on!
This way!
Open it up!
Mor!
Come on!
Further, Tuk.
We can't get out!
- We'll stay together, okay?
- Yes.
All courage is, help us!
Skin!
- Bridge!
- Mother and father are down there.
- Grab. - I'm ready.
Okay.
Jake!
Far?
Pis!
Come on, you fool.
- Breathe, Dad. - Neteyam?
No, it's Lo'ak.
- Oh, Lo'ak... - Sorry.
- Neteyam's death is my fault.
- Just concentrate on the present.
The air pocket disappears. We
have to go out. Come on, Dad.
- Can you find out from here?
- Yes, but it will be a long dive.
I can't handle it. But
you can. Hurry out.
I can't lose you too, Dad.
Mom, I'm scared.
It will be OK. Stick
with me. Stick to mom.
It will probably work.
You just need to calm your
heart and be completely calm.
Breathe from down here.
The being of water has
no beginning and no end.
The sea is around
you and in you.
The sea is your home before
your birth and after your death.
The sea gives and the sea takes.
Water ties everything together.
Life and death.
The dark and the light.
- Hi. - Kiri!
It'll be fine, little
sister. Mom, I give you this.
It will help you.
Dad, you're good.
Trust me. Say your heart.
Deep breaths.
Last breath.
Follow me.
Hang on. Just breathe.
So.
I see you, my son.
MaJake!
Far! Far!
Came. Come here.
- Tuck! - I have you.
Brother.
Sully is a stickler.
That was our biggest weakness -
- and our great strength.
Thank you, Al mod er. Thanks.
Let's get away.
My boy...
Come along.
Spider!
Abekat!
Spider.
- Are you all right? - Yes.
Come here.
A son for a son.
All singing cords
have a final bead.
A father protects. That
is his purpose in life.
The people say that all
energy is only borrowed.
One day you have
to give it back.
Eywa takes care of
all her children.
Nothing ever goes away.
Not finished!
My family and I are
leaving tomorrow.
Far away from here.
Your son is with our ancestors.
You are metkayinas now.
That's how it happened.
We are sea people now.
This is our home.
Sheep! Look what I caught!
Wow, that's a big crab.
It was over there by the
rocks, just like you said.
What's the matter, dad?
Why are you crying?
I'm just glad to see you.
I'm glad to see you too.
You try.
Okay.
- Have you left me any? - Maybe.
Now look there.
Now I see it. I can't save
my family by running away.
This is our home, our fortress.
This is where we stand.
Retail by YOLO,
Edited by Firewalker
Translation: Henrik Thøgersen
Scandinavian Text Service