- He doesn't want to come out.
- What?
He wants to stay inside.
Why?
He says the world's too fucked up.
Do you have any allergies?
- No, but...
- Please, don't move.
- Okay.
- Open your legs, please.
Just breathe.
- Relax.
- Yes.
You can do it, little guy.
That's it. It's over.
- You did well.
- Great job.
That's it.
Well done.
- What happened?
- He decided to stay inside.
- Who?
- Mateo. He doesn't want to come out.
I saw some scissors back there.
Now what?
I don't know.
How's he going to feed himself?
He'll eat me, I guess.
And you.
BARDO, FALSE CHRONICLE
OF A HANDFUL OF TRUTHS
Welcome aboard the Metro Expo Line.
This train's final destination is
Downtown Santa Monica station.
The next stop
is Expo Park/USC station.
Is that normal?
That sound. Is it normal?
Thanks for going Metro.
Your safety is our top priority.
Help us help you by keeping
your valuables and money out of sight.
Report any activity
by calling Metro's law enforcement
and security hotline at 888-950-SAFE.
If you see something, say something.
The next stop is
La Cienega/Jefferson station.
What most believed
to be a rumor now appears to be reality.
After weeks of increasing tension
between the two countries, Carlos Soler...
Shit.
...United Mexican States,
visited the White House today to meet
with Halbrook's secretary of state.
Not many details are known,
but our sources assure us
that the US government
may have approved Amazon's plan
of buying the Mexican state
of Baja California.
That's right, you heard it.
Amazon, the American multinational,
is interested in buying
the Mexican state of Baja California
and has the full support
of the US government.
This is all Presidents Halbrook and Soler
had to say at today's press conference.
Borderlines are human-made.
These must be subordinated to human needs.
By moving down the border,
a third-world territory
could maybe even become
a first-world promised land.
Mexican President Soler
and I want this historic transaction
to be an homage for both of our countries.
We must celebrate
this economic integration
of imperial dimensions.
Negotiation, not invasion.
It is the Mexican people
this sale will benefit...
He's been waiting.
Ambassador Jones.
Oh, Mr. Gama.
Have they moved you into the castle?
No, there's just
some event here this evening,
and the Mexican government's
asked me to say a few words.
But they're rehearsing this afternoon.
I'm sorry to make you come out this far.
No, no. It's fine. It's fine.
For a minute, I thought President Halbrook
had appointed you emperor of Mexico.
Not yet.
What's going on out there?
Well, as you are well aware, we are having
a celebration for the 175th anniversary
of the end of the Mexican-American War.
"Celebration"?
Well, a... a tribute.
Yeah, to be fair, it was not a war.
It was an invasion.
Young men on both sides
pointed guns at one another.
So many lives lost.
Yeah, you lost a few thousand.
We lost way more than that
and half of our country.
Well, to be fair, you didn't lose.
Well, that's true
because you just took it.
- We paid for it.
- Yeah.
Yeah, 15 million pesos.
Well, let's not talk about the past.
Would you like some tea?
No, thank you.
I've been trying to get an interview
with President Halbrook for months.
I went as far
as promising his chief of staff
to landscape
the White House lawn for free.
Oh, you!
I think I might be able
to finally help you.
Really?
What would you say
to an exclusive interview,
you and the president,
one hour, in the Oval Office?
- Are you being serious, now?
- I am.
Though we'd need you to do something.
Oh, I figured as much, yeah.
The president knows you are
an important voice in Latin America.
We've been working
for months on this new deal.
- That's why I want to talk to him.
- Listen.
It is essential
that this administration build a bridge
with the Latin community
and with Mexico in particular.
And with you winning this Alethea Award,
you'll move front and center
in the world of serious journalism.
You know I'm not going to agree
to change my speech.
- I thought you hadn't written it.
- I haven't.
So, you won't have to change it, then.
And maybe with this exclusive interview
in mind, you find a new thread.
Steven!
Anyway, think about it.
Do you mind?
Here we go.
Let me walk you out.
So, how's your family?
Oh, fine.
Fine, thank you. Everybody's fine.
Now, you're gonna have
to show me around here.
I used to come here
when I was a kid.
Did you study here?
No, they brought us here
to learn about the Niños Héroes.
You know what that is?
Oh, yeah.
No. No, I don't.
Toward the end
of the Mexican-American War,
a group of students, cadets,
were surrounded by American soldiers,
right here in this castle.
The reality is
they were simply slaughtered.
But with time,
a myth was formed around that event.
What myth?
Go, go!
Move, move!
Go, go, go, go!
They were kids.
Yeah.
That's why we call them the Boy Heroes.
Exalted compatriots!
Before it falls in the hands of the enemy,
I take with me the flag of the fatherland!
May the myth rise over Mexico
and give shelter to us forevermore!
¡Viva México, cabrones!
Oh, fuck.
Have you written your speech yet?
Oh, only Mexicans can turn
disgraceful defeat into mythic victory.
Señor Silverio?
- Got a headache?
- A little.
The altitude and the pollution
always kill me
my first few days back in Mexico.
The same happens to my dad
when he comes back to the capital.
He says Mexico's not a country
but a state of mind.
That's a good one. How is your dad?
Good. Stuck in Oaxaca.
His emphysema's killing him.
That's too bad. Say hi to him for me.
Sure. You want me to stop at a pharmacy?
Nah. Thanks, Antonio.
So I heard on the radio you're going to be
on Luis Valdivia's TV show.
Yeah. I didn't want to,
but you know how Lucía is.
She forced me to take the invite.
But... didn't you see what he said
about your last documentary?
Luis? No. What'd he say?
Nothing good, sir.
He said you were worse than Malinche.
That you disrespected journalism
and who knows what else.
It's docufiction, Antonio.
If you don't know how to play around,
you don't deserve to be taken seriously.
Truth is, I didn't watch
your documentary, sir.
But I did see that guy on TV,
and he pissed me off.
Luis is wrapping up a meeting,
but he told me
he'll find you in makeup, okay?
Congratulations, maestro.
Welcome back.
Thanks!
Hey, when's the last time
you were on here?
Oof.
More than 30 years ago, I guess.
Thirty? That's my age.
Welcome again. Go ahead.
Welcome.
Hey, can you open up?
We're back on Bocaguanga.
We've got a breaking story
you won't believe.
No one lifted a finger to help him.
At the train's last stop,
he was the last passenger.
Fucking gringos.
A cleaning lady found him.
A compatriot of ours,
Ms. Refugio Domínguez.
Hello, Refugio.
- Hi.
- We caught up with her.
We'll have the pleasure
of speaking with her.
Thanks for joining us.
Tell us what happened.
I went in to clean the train car,
as usual, and saw it wasn't empty.
I thought at first the guy might be
a drunk because that's common here.
But then I saw the fish on the floor.
They were all dead...
Come on!
Yeah! Go on! Attention!
Don't go! I...
- ...seven, eight...
- You can't go there!
Wait! Wait! Wait!
Silverio, I... Sorry. I'm sorry!
Silverio, wait. Wait.
Stop! Stop! Stop! Stop! Stop! Stop!
You're out of sync!
- Tania, I said to the right!
- Fuck you! What do you know?
Tania, it's always the same shit with you!
Everyone, take your positions.
Priscilla, on your mark.
Five, six, seven, eight.
This way.
We are here. I'm going to leave you here.
- Thanks.
- No problem.
Do my eyes deceive me?
Hello, Marta.
Silverio Gama.
I thought you stepped on a landmine
in Afghanistan and got blown to bits.
I'm still here. In one piece. For now.
- How long has it been?
- Ages.
Centuries.
- Sorry, I was really...
- Busy. I know.
But you could have found a minute
between documentaries to visit me.
Come on, sit down.
- Is this what you're wearing?
- Should I take it off?
Yeah, right?
Luis tried very hard
to be happy for you.
He sent me six bottles of prosecco.
That's his way
of congratulating you without saying it.
He never got over you abandoning him.
I didn't abandon him.
I left for a year,
and it turned into 20.
I ran away from the censors,
and now look where we are.
Hmm.
I worked hard to make a name for myself
as an independent journalist,
then as a filmmaker.
My mother still thinks
it was the worst decision of my life.
Luis could have gone too.
No one put a gun to his head.
Well, one time he criticized
the ineptitude of Mexico's president
and his apostles, and...
The head of the station
comes through swinging his dick,
calls him while he's on air,
and nearly strings him up
by his balls on stage.
It's a miracle he's still got his show.
There are no heroes on this channel.
We all eat the same shit.
We're terrified of losing
what little we've got.
Tania?
What?
Tania Kristel?
What are you looking at?
Sorry.
Do I know you?
No, but I know you.
I used to watch you on TV all the time.
What are you thinking?
Don Silverio Gama!
- Luis, my man.
- Where have you been, cabrón?
Hey.
Welcome back.
Give me a hug, cabrón.
Leave him alone, Marta.
I will when I'm done.
There's no fixing that face.
Give me five.
- Don't move.
- What are you doing?
- Epic. My Twitter's going to blow up.
- Enough!
Don't be an asshole, cabrón.
Look at him.
He's still mad
I left him in the lurch, right?
Furious!
I've got the top-rated talk show
in Mexico, Papá.
Yeah, you only interview YouTubers.
Nice stuff.
That's news too, isn't it?
Ready.
Give me a hug, bro.
- I missed you. Here is where we started.
- That's right.
- How many days are you staying? Huh?
- Not many.
Did you already prepare
your speech for the ceremony?
No.
Oof. I figured.
Hey, I loved your last documentary,
False Chronicle of a Handful of Truths.
- Crazy stuff.
- You liked it?
Tons.
But the part where you share a smoke
with Hernán Cortés was a bit much.
How are you supposed to know
what Cortés or Juan Escutia was thinking?
Did you run out of living people
to interview, or what?
- You already working on the next one?
- Yeah, I mean, I'm raising money.
It's going to be months of research,
lots of travel.
I don't know how you can spend
so much time on one thing.
The world changes
with every week, every day, every tweet.
- Ten seconds.
- My questions?
- I already gave them to you.
- I don't have my questions.
Wait, yeah. I've got them. Good to go.
Come on! Come on!
Relax.
Welcome to another episode
of Let's Suppose.
We've got a special show today.
Here with me is my close friend
and former copresenter
on the eight o'clock news, Silverio Gama.
Renowned documentary filmmaker
and the first, that's right,
the first Mexican to receive
the Alethea Award for journalistic ethics,
given every four years
by the American Society of Journalists.
You'll be getting it
in Los Angeles in just a few days.
This interview is sponsored
by Los Molinos Coffee.
Mm.
Simply delicious.
How are you?
How do you feel being back in your Mexico?
I can't imagine how nervous you are.
There's a lot riding on this award, no?
Silverio?
Are you with us?
Can we check his mic?
I think we've got a mic problem.
My apologies.
This is the risk of doing live TV.
Let me shoot straight, Silverio.
Some of our colleagues say
American liberals are using you,
and this award is to compensate for
the far right's attacks on our country.
Are you aware of this?
Let's suppose
they're giving you this award
to please a community full of Mexicans...
...in Los Angeles.
Do you not want to talk about it?
Let's talk about your private life, then.
As the great Sainte-Beuve said,
a man's private life, what he does,
the decisions he makes every day,
even what he eats, all define his work.
Is it true it upset you
that they called you "darky" as a child?
That it embarrassed your mother
and grandmother that you looked,
well, darker than you should?
More Indigenous than white?
Was that disdain real?
It's your family, no?
Señor...
Alejandra Bravo told us, on Instagram...
Remember your first girlfriend?
At 16, you ran away with her
to have a great adventure,
but you refused
to take off your underwear!
Because you were scared
of God's wrath, of hell...
What were you thinking?
You'd show up
at the altar a virgin?
The great Silverio Gama
was a dark-skinned car washer,
a chump, a two-bit radio announcer.
But today he has an honorary degree
from the UNAM.
He's a Chevalier des Arts in France,
and he didn't even finish college.
He's an entitled bougie bastard
on a mission to portray misery
and poverty and society's outcasts,
but he's best friends
with this station's owner.
And his family supports
the Club América de Fútbol.
How's the "guard dog
of the truth" feel on the receiving end?
You spent years making TV ads
for capitalism,
but all of a sudden you're an artiste.
I guess our friend
doesn't feel like talking.
A word to the wise is sufficient.
Amazing, Silverio.
You'll gladly run your trap
for the gringos and whoever else,
but here you clam up.
A real shame.
We'll take a quick commercial break.
We'll be back.
Silverio.
Can you hear me?
I got held up.
Where are you?
I was trying to get
an interview with Halbrook.
I feel you can hear me.
I hear you, Lucía.
There you are.
- Where'd you get off to?
- I don't know.
- What do you mean?
- I was out and about.
Why didn't you go
to your interview with Luis?
You want something to drink?
The Let's Suppose producers
haven't stopped calling.
Uh-huh.
- I didn't know what to say.
- I'll call them later.
Luis was calling all day. He's furious.
He told me they spent
the whole week hyping up the interview.
You're the one who accepted.
I didn't want to go.
So now it's my fault.
I was afraid they'd humiliate me,
make me a laughingstock.
Why would they?
Because the whole thing's a joke.
What is?
I go around seeking approval
from people who despise me.
I act before I think,
hoping to get what I want, then when I do,
I detest it.
And I'm ashamed I ever wanted it.
What are you talking about?
I spend
my life convincing myself
of the importance of what I do,
of the value of recognition.
Then when it comes, I feel nothing.
The one thing I feel
is I don't deserve it.
- Of course you deserve it.
- What do I deserve? That's hubris.
Your lack of humility is hubris, Silverio.
You always do the same thing.
You work and hide in a corner for years,
and when you show your work,
get recognition,
you turn bitter, give up,
get depressed, and play the victim.
- I know.
- It's exhausting, Silverio.
There are many things
I'd like to change, but I can't.
And believe me, I've tried.
Your imposter syndrome
is pathetic.
You could have at least called.
That's what Luis
and everyone else thinks.
- They all know it.
- It's craziness.
You inevitably turn into
what you think others think you are.
All anyone's interested in
are the inanities of our personal life.
Otherwise, nothing we do matters to them.
And you're just figuring that out now?
Not going was worse.
Luis is smearing you all over the web.
Now it's not an audience laughing,
it's his three million followers.
Look what he posted.
I'm telling you,
life is nothing
but a series of idiotic images.
Exposure at any price.
Repeating the same scenes of us shitting,
wiping our asses, and being ridiculed.
Quit it.
- What?
- Your lips aren't moving.
Does that bother you?
- Yeah, quit it.
- Fine, I'll stop.
Ow.
Sooner or later, you'll have to call him.
I know.
How dare you leave him hanging
on a live TV show?
I'm going to Uruapan.
When?
I already told you. Tomorrow.
It's the biggest fair,
and I can't let Lucero go alone.
I've been gone too long.
So...?
It's got to be today, then.
What choice do we have?
Ah!
Lucía?
I found you.
Hmm.
Will you marry me?
Ow!
Lucía?
Dad...
Dad.
Lorenzo?
What time is it?
Late... Early. I don't know.
You don't have to get up for a while.
- I had a nice dream.
- What did you dream?
You were chasing Mom around the apartment.
You were both laughing.
Mom had her boobies out.
You saw us?
No, it was just a dream.
But...
I had a nightmare afterward.
Uh-huh.
I had a clear plastic tube
in my mouth,
and it was blowing all this air,
and I swelled up like a balloon.
I couldn't breathe.
It was blocking my throat.
So... I pulled it out... with my hands.
Talk softer.
You're going to wake up your sister.
She's not going to wake up.
She's asleep, same as me.
No.
There were people
in the windows watching me,
but they didn't say anything.
- My brother Mateo was there too.
- Ah.
And the people left,
and you sat down on my bed
and looked at me with sad eyes.
As you are looking at me now,
and that's what I'm dreaming.
And so are you.
- But we're awake.
- No. I'm dreaming you.
- You can't dream that you're dreaming.
- I can.
- No.
- Yes, I can.
Does this hurt?
- No.
- Really?
What about now?
- No.
- And now?
No, because I'm dreaming.
Here's what we'll do, then.
I'll cut off a lock of your hair
and put it in the nightstand.
If you find it when you wake up tomorrow,
that means we're awake. Huh?
Here we go.
Good night.
Dad?
Huh?
Paco's sick.
How do you know?
There are worms.
Looks fine to me.
- Dad?
- Yes?
Why's it called Los Angeles?
I don't know.
Are there angels in Los Angeles?
Maybe. Get some sleep.
- Dad?
- Eh?
I don't want to leave them here.
- Who?
- Paco, Guido, and Ernesto.
I want us to take them.
We'll talk about that tomorrow.
It's sleepy time now.
Where were you?
- You didn't close the door.
- It doesn't matter.
They can't hear us.
What are you doing?
He's back.
Again?
Push him back in.
- What is it?
- He doesn't want to go.
Wait.
He keeps coming back.
I think he wanted
to tell us something this time.
He's a baby. What's he going to say?
- He's trying to blame us.
- For what?
For the distance between us.
For my selfishness.
Remember how I blew up the night before?
That's why we lost him.
We didn't lose him.
He chose not to come.
Mm-hmm.
Lorenzo told me
he saw Mateo in a dream.
How could he dream of him
if Lorenzo was born a year later?
It doesn't matter. They remember him.
We told the kids
over and over that Mateo wasn't here
because he was flying around heaven
with his little wings.
Remember?
Mateo's just an idea now.
He's not a person.
People come and go.
Ideas are what remain.
- I don't remember his face.
- Mm.
How can a child just transform
into a vague memory?
He didn't give me the chance.
To what?
I know I can be a good father.
Poor little boy.
If I saw that face of yours, I'd want
to crawl back inside my mother too.
He must have been horrified
when he saw you.
Poor Lorenzo and Camila
didn't have a choice.
They have to look at this mug every day.
We should let Mateo go.
We could start
by taking him out of this room.
Mm-hmm.
We need to find a new place for him.
Somewhere he can rest.
Get up, Silverio.
I'm making breakfast.
Who's coming?
Hello? Come on up.
- It's Miguel.
- Miguel who?
The hairdresser. He's been here before.
- So early?
- They're picking us up at 7:00 p.m.
It's 10:00 a.m. Will you spend nine hours
with your hair done up?
Yeah, for you. You should be grateful.
You could have shut the door last night
before doing whatever you were doing.
Good morning, Lorenzo. How'd you sleep?
I barely fit
in the fucking bed.
I'm making eggs.
Does anyone want some?
No, I'm fine.
- Silverio? Eggs?
- Hmm?
Who's that?
Miguel.
- Miguel who?
- The hairdresser.
Hola.
Go into the living room.
I'll meet you there.
Today's
the journalist union party.
- I thought it was tomorrow.
- No, today.
Thanks for being so nice with Miguel.
Hey, what do you think of this?
- What is it?
- My neighborhood. Narvarte.
Martín wants us to start the video
with images and photos of my roots.
I like the idea, but don't use that music.
Boring.
Why?
Dad, who gives a shit about roots?
We all come from somewhere.
Not everyone knows where I'm from.
But you're right.
If I don't care, who the fuck would?
Do you want to watch a movie?
Moo... mie.
- What do you think of this?
- No!
Who is that? Me?
No, you can't put that on.
It's embarrassing.
I'll forbid you.
Where'd you find that?
I haven't heard it in years.
- We recorded it on the way to Zihuatanejo.
- Mom, stop.
Your dad and I recorded everything
for the first... what? Twelve years?
Every sound on every trip we took.
We even recorded your farts.
Wait, listen to this.
Is that Japan?
Incredible.
- Please don't use that.
- Why not?
It's our life soundtrack.
Jesus, wash your hair.
What time is Camila coming?
After lunch.
She's going to call me when she lands.
Your chilaquiles are ready.
You need to eat, Silverio.
You've got a long day.
There are no eggs.
- I'll be back. I'm going with Miguel.
- No eggs?
What's that now?
One of my strangest
and most emotional documentaries.
On their way
to the US border to seek asylum,
the people in the caravan stopped to pray
at the Cerro de las Piedras.
And Our Lady of San Juan de los Lagos
appeared.
There were many of them,
but they never made it to the border.
When we tried to find them,
all that was left was their clothes,
some belongings.
No sign of the bodies.
Some people told us
that Our Lady of San Juan de los Lagos
came to take them away.
Maybe it was an answer
to so much faith and despair.
- And you believe it?
- No.
I don't believe anything until I see it.
But a documentarian
shouldn't believe or not believe.
He just needs to look
and know where to focus.
And some of these people
told the camera incredible stories.
- You're going to put that in your video?
- Yeah, I think so.
Why?
Because that's a big part
of what we are, a country of immigrants.
These people make sacrifices
and leave everything behind
because here they're nothing.
They're looking for something better.
Cleaning the bathrooms
at an In-N-Out is better?
Yeah, for many of them, it is.
No. They go 'cause they want to.
We left too.
No, it's not the same.
Why not?
We left everything here.
Yeah,
but they don't have a choice.
They leave because there's no work.
Here, people kill them, extort them.
We didn't lack anything.
We're first-class immigrants.
I don't get it.
What?
How is this representing you?
Why use these people
to talk about your life
if you don't know
who they are or how they live?
You shoot them, you interview them,
you even make money with them,
but you don't know them at all.
Who made you king shit?
What?
You're 17 years old,
and you act like you know everything.
When I was your age,
I was on a fishing boat, working.
Here you go.
The stupid boat. C'mon.
That's what happens
when you give someone everything
and they never learn shit.
You don't appreciate anything
because you've never worked for it.
You've got no responsibilities.
It's your fault.
What?
You brought me to the world.
No one told me.
No one ever warns you about it.
Your kid becomes a teenager,
and it's a full-time job.
Everything's a fucking problem.
Wow,
I didn't ask you to bring me here.
You realize that, right?
That you don't respect anyone or anything.
Not even your parents.
And those people
whose lives you find depressing,
at least they respect who they are,
their ancestors, their customs...
Their rituals existed way before the USA,
a country that only respects money,
learned to walk.
You don't know them.
And that's the truth. It's not your truth.
No. But how can you know
if I appreciate things or not?
I do appreciate things
but not the ones you do.
And yes, things cost me a lot.
Even now, expressing my feelings,
which you insist I should do.
Yes, I insist.
It costs me a lot,
but I do it.
Just, they're not the feelings
you would like, so they must not be true.
Speak Spanish.
Why?
Because we're in Mexico,
we're Mexicans, and we speak Spanish!
You couldn't pick up the phone?
Hello?
You always do the same, Dad.
Every time we come to Mexico,
you try to convince me of how cool,
deep, spiritual, and cultural it is.
But it's not.
People suffer and starve.
Stop.
If you love Mexico so much,
why'd you take Camila
and me to the States?
- Why did you make us grow up there?
- Bye.
That was Reynolds.
He said the award rehearsal
is next Tuesday at 5:00 p.m. LA time.
Congratulations.
You're the big shit, Dad.
That country that only respects
for money is going to give you an award.
And you're going to go get it.
I'm just looking forward
to hear what you will say.
Our Lady of Los Lagos
didn't make those immigrants disappear.
They disappeared
because they fucking died.
- You know you're no different, right?
- What?
If someone praises Mexico,
you lecture them about how it is.
If a gringo criticizes it, you recite why
it's the most fascinating gastronomical,
anthropological, and cultural experiment
the world's ever known.
Lucía, all I'm saying
is you have to leave Mexico
to realize what you've lost
and what they've stolen and destroyed.
Lorenzo was trying to tell you
he thinks it's a poor country.
It's not poor, it's unequal.
There's a difference.
Perfect. You win again, Silverio.
Your justifications are faultless.
As always.
When's the last time
you strolled in the city?
Let it go.
You really want another chance?
- At what?
- At being a good father.
- Yeah.
- Well, you've got one.
With Lorenzo and Camila.
They're still young.
You just need to learn to be present.
I'm here, Lucía.
Yeah, with your laptop,
working on your fucking award video.
I'm going
to pick up the clothes!
This desert is a killing machine.
If the heat and mountains don't kill you,
a snake or a scorpion will.
Where are you going?
Arizona.
We'll cross through Nogales.
We're taking the god Centéotl
so they'll bring him back to life.
What happened
to the god Centéotl?
He died.
There's no corn left.
We're starving to death.
You don't have to die
to go to hell.
Just go to Chalchihuites,
and you'll find it.
There, in our village,
everything is death, hunger, violence.
Are there more people with you?
Our grandkids.
Back there,
they've got Centéotl.
My two kids were killed.
So we're going north to meet my brother.
Thanks.
Safe travels.
Do you have enough water?
There she is! They found her!
Listen to my sister! She's on the phone!
She says Our Lady of Los Lagos appeared
to them on the Cerro de las Piedras.
As they reached the top of the hill,
night turned to day.
And then she appeared!
She's blessing them!
Silverio...
Silverio, how are you feeling?
You seem tired.
Peaceful.
Tranquil.
♪ I got sunshine in my stomach ♪
♪ Like I just rocked my baby to sleep ♪
♪ But I can't keep me
From creeping sleep ♪
♪ Sleep, deep in the deep ♪
You're not scared?
Scared of what?
Of dying.
For you people,
death is a Christian affair.
A comfortable heart attack in bed.
For us, it's our daily bread.
Getting tossed in a mass grave.
Here in jail,
no one can come in and kill me.
But I can have you killed out there.
I used to be poor, invisible.
You all ignored me for decades.
Now... I've got you by the balls.
We're walking bombs.
There are millions of us
in the poor villages.
We stand at the heart of the paradox.
We're a new species.
A different beast. We're not like you.
What should we have done?
You intellectuals
love running your mouths
about class struggle, the marginalized.
Then we show up.
The proletariat, the dejected,
the exploited, all that's old news.
There's something new growing out there,
raised in the mud,
schooled on the purest illiteracy,
and it lurks like an alien monster
in the corners of the city.
You're looking at
what you might call "post-poverty."
What changed out in the slums?
Cash. We've got millions,
and you are all bankrupt
and are led by incompetents.
Damn straight!
Get it?
Our methods are agile,
you're slow and bureaucratic.
We don't fear death, you're dying of fear.
We pack real guns,
you pack .38s.
We attack, you defend.
You say "human rights," we say "no mercy."
You've made us TV stars,
we've made you clowns.
The slum dwellers help us,
out of love or fear, but they hate you.
You're regional, provincial,
nationalist, corrupt.
We've got 50 million
captive gringo junkies.
Our guns come from overseas,
from the Yankees.
We're global.
We don't forget about you.
You're our customers.
You forget us as soon as the shock
of the violence we provoke has passed.
HONORARY MEMBER
OF THE MEXICAN JOURNALISTS UNION
CALIFORNIA DANCING CLUB
How's it feel being
in front of the camera?
What's going
through your head now?
If I told you what I was thinking
right now, I'd get locked up for life.
Do you feel more gringo or more Mexican?
My nationality is no nationality.
Do you understand
what's going on in your country?
No. Honestly, I can't understand
my country.
All I can do is love it.
How should we respond to
the most dangerous cartel on the planet?
The corporate cartel of the USA.
Silverio!
Will you take a photo with me?
Sure. Thanks.
- Thanks.
- I love your work.
- I love your work too.
Thank you. Good night.
Hey!
That arrogant son of a bitch.
- No mezcal around?
- I saw a waiter serving some over there.
Dad!
Darling! It's good to see you!
The flight was delayed.
It won't stop snowing in Boston.
Ah!
What's up, bro?
So this whole party's
just for you?
So it seems.
Horrible. Come on,
my aunts and uncles are over there.
- The whole family's waiting for you.
- Where are they?
- In the back, Mom.
Brother-in-law!
Who paid for this blowout?
Thought you journalists were broke.
No matter if they treat you nice or bad,
you bitch anyway.
- Have a fucking drink. They're free.
- In that case...
- My darky!
- My dear sister!
- I loved the documentary. So much.
- So good. But a little whiny, no?
And a little long.
It's 90 minutes long, you lazy bum.
No, no, no, no! Oh, wow!
- The jewel in the crown.
- I clean up pretty good, don't I?
Maybe you can stick me in your next film,
even just in the corner
as an extra.
Congratulations.
You finally made it, you bastard!
I missed you guys.
It's a miracle, cabrón!
My daughter got married, you bailed.
My father died, you bailed.
But they throw a party for you,
and here you are.
You think his lordship
will come to our bullshit get-togethers?
Good to see you. Congratulations, cabrón.
They won't leave you alone.
They're disguised complaints, brother.
Who'd have thought you'd get an award
from the same bastards
you've been criticizing your whole life?
I know, right?
- You've got something on your nose.
- What?
Ah.
A piece of shit
from kissing all that gringo ass.
Honestly, considering you're
such a dumbass, you surprised all of us.
Piss off.
Seriously, though. I really admire you.
Thanks. I admire you too.
- Keep your feet on the ground, eh?
- How about you lift your fat ass off it?
He fucking got me!
He's calling me a loser, cabrón.
Go back to the other side
and kiss some more Mexican ass.
Don't fuck with him.
You'll wind up in the papers.
Look who's coming! Pablo Galindo!
Pablito, run and hide, cabrón.
You don't want word getting out
about your beach mansion in Baja.
I couldn't give a fuck, pal.
Here's to Silverio.
A toast!
- Cheers!
Give me a cigarette.
These people are driving me nuts.
- Who is that?
- Where?
Over there. The art critic.
I forgot his name.
As usual.
Hey, Luis.
Thanks for showing up.
Thanks for not inviting me, cabrón.
Lucía, how are you?
- Good, Luis. So nice you came.
- Thanks.
- I'm going for a mezcal. Want anything?
- No, thanks. I'm good.
- Mezcal, thanks.
- Okay.
The illustrious Don Silverio Gama.
Journalist, documentarian/artist.
The icon looking down on us
from his pedestal.
Who neither shows up for his interview,
nor cares about the efforts made
by an entire live TV crew.
I'm sorry, Luis.
'Cause to you,
everyone at this party is just a peon.
Yeah, each and every one of us.
But you're wrong.
Those of us who didn't hightail it
out of Mexico, we're martyrs.
- Luis, I swear...
- Ditching me wasn't enough, Silverio?
I've been trying to find you for days.
Why didn't you face me?
I know. I'm sorry, I am.
Why?
Uh, Luis, I'm thankful
you invited me on your show, but...
But what, cabrón?
I just couldn't do it.
- My show isn't good enough for you?
- Don't do this to me. Please.
You and I are friends.
Exactly, cabrón.
And when friends call, you pick up.
You shoot straight. Especially you.
Mr. Truth, Mr. Critical Thinking.
Give me a break.
Come on, please.
You've trashed my work publicly
thousands of times.
Luis, why did you invite me?
What do you mean, "why?"
If you hate my work so much, why bother?
I'm a journalist, not your fan or lackey.
You're my friend, and I think
that's what you've come to proclaim.
But if you were, you'd say
the truth to my face, not publicly.
- You want the truth?
- I do.
Want to know
what I think of your documentary?
Shoot. I can handle it.
I think it's pretentious.
It's pointlessly oneiric.
It's oneiric to cover up
for your mediocre writing.
It's a mishmash of pointless scenes.
Half the time, I wanted to crack up,
the other half I was dying of boredom.
It's supposed to be metaphorical,
but it lacks poetic inspiration.
It feels stolen. Plagiarized.
And you barely covered your tracks.
What's so funny? It's banal, random.
That shit with the soldiers
in blond wigs at Chapultepec Castle...
Come on.
First the guy's
on the train with some axolotls.
Then bang, he's in his apartment
in the middle of the desert.
Just because. 'Cause that's
how it popped into your head.
Why there and not,
say, the Estadio Azteca?
- Why not?
- Because life isn't like that, man.
There's chronology.
Order. Causes and consequences.
It's a docufiction, Luis.
Humor's serious business.
Unintentional humor because you broke
every rule of good journalism.
Fuck objectivity, neutrality,
history, truth.
You couldn't check your ego.
You even put yourself
in the movie, cabrón.
You used historical figures
to talk about yourself.
Who the fuck do you think you are?
Answer, cabrón!
Gimme a smoke.
If you want to talk about your life,
tell it straight.
Write an autobiography.
Screw that. Nothing could be more boring
or banal than my life.
What the fuck were you trying to say?
You talk about your private life
or the cosmos,
your personal tragedies or politics.
What was that? A memoir, a farce, or...
I'm all those things
and none of them, Luis.
You sound like an artiste.
Maybe it's just a chronicle
of uncertainties.
That suits me fine.
You've got to be crazy.
A chronicle of uncertainties? Fuck.
Luis, I'm not interested
in talking about my life.
Memory lacks truth.
All it has is emotional conviction.
Anyway, I'm tired of saying
what I think and not what I feel.
You're a journalist.
You have to say what you think
and think what you say.
At least you used to have solid ideas.
What good are solid ideas
in a world that slips through our fingers?
You're getting old, buddy.
A clear case of a midlife crisis.
Could be.
At this age, life goes so fast,
it starts to feel like a convulsion.
A tumult of images, memories, slivers,
all knotted together.
How beautiful this ugly city is,
don't you think?
For fuck's sake, man.
- Sorry to interrupt.
- No problem.
Luis Valdivia, can we take a photo?
- Of course.
- Thank you.
- In the middle, please.
- Yes.
Perfect.
One, two...
Excellent.
Thanks so much.
We're huge fans of your show.
Thanks. Good night.
Just don't forget, Silverio,
where you come from
or who you were before you met me.
What are you laughing at, dickhead?
At your fucking certainties, cabrón.
Categorical, like your journalism.
Blinkered, like your acumen.
As mediocre as your artistic aptitudes.
I'm laughing at your short-sighted,
flag-waving nationalism.
Your provincialism.
How you bow down to an industry
devoted to public humiliation
and online lynching.
The clicks that tell us what to believe.
The new gold mine for corporations.
Luis, I am who I am because I got away
from you, from here, from TV.
Look at you.
Vulgar.
Spiteful. And proud of it to boot.
You're a fake.
Scrounging for likes on your socials.
Strolling around with your goons.
Rubbing elbows with the president,
pushing faddish ideologies and idiocies.
You're the perfect image
of today's journalist, Luis.
An entertainer, an opinion peddler.
It's people like you
who've left us without truth.
Beat it. Go dance.
I'm tired of hearing you.
Tough men don't dance.
That's my father's line,
and I forbid you to use it.
Go, I'm sick of hearing your voice.
Mm.
I told you I'm sick of your voice.
- Finally.
- How was it with Luis?
Tell me.
Marvelous.
Seriously?
Come on. Let's dance.
- Let's have a mezcal.
- Let's dance instead.
Please.
- No, wait!
- Let's dance.
I don't feel like it.
There are 100 guys here
who'd kill for a dance with me.
Oh,
it seems the jungle's calling.
- Hey!
Come on!
Dad!
You recognize this song?
- Which one?
- This one.
- Silverio!
- Cloe!
♪ Ah ♪
♪ Let's dance ♪
♪ Put on your red shoes
And dance the blues ♪
♪ Let's dance ♪
♪ To the song
They're playin' on the radio ♪
♪ Let's sway ♪
♪ While color lights up your face ♪
♪ Sway through the crowd
To an empty space ♪
♪ If you say run ♪
♪ I'll run with you ♪
♪ And if you say hide ♪
- ♪ We'll hide ♪
- ♪ Hide, hide, hide ♪
♪ Because my love for you ♪
♪ Would break my heart in two ♪
♪ If you should fall into my arms ♪
♪ And tremble like a flower ♪
My apologies.
The festivities will continue in a moment.
Before we invite up our guest of honor,
we'll hear a few words
from our esteemed
secretary of the interior,
Mr. Siniestro Quiñones.
Let's give him a round of applause.
Thank you. Thank you so much.
This celebration
will close with a major award.
An award that fills us with pride,
that for the first time
will be given to a Mexican
or Latin American journalist.
- Where's the guest of honor?
- Silverio!
Come up and say a few words.
- Dad, where are you going?
- Where is he?
- Silverio!
- He'll be here soon.
- Silverio! Silverio! Silverio!
- It seems he's missing.
- Silverio! Silverio!
- Let's all shout his name!
Silverio! Silverio!
I've said my piece.
Now it's Silverio's turn.
Silverio! Silverio! Silverio!
MEN'S RESTROOM
What is this?
Impossible.
My little boy has turned so gray.
I'm nearly your age, Pa.
You're an old man now.
Age comes without warning.
Then it turns into a full-time job.
Walking, eating, using the bathroom...
everything's a problem.
No one ever told me.
Nobody ever warns you about it.
I'm glad you came.
How could I miss my boy's party?
I'm sorry your mother couldn't be here.
The thought that I'll never be
with her again is unbearable.
But sometimes I visit her
in her room and pull her by the legs.
Son...
I'm so sorry I never told you
how proud I am of you.
You did, though, Pa.
In your way. Without saying it.
I realized that eventually.
You were a great father.
I lost all I had.
That's why I couldn't be more.
A father and sometimes a husband.
But I was always ashamed
of what I could have been but wasn't.
But you, you're a man of the world.
- Yeah.
- You're very successful.
Mm-hmm.
And you were such a loser.
I promise, your mother
and I never saw this coming.
I know.
Me neither.
You know, sometimes
I'm also ashamed of what I am
and what I should have been.
Are you okay?
It sure would have helped me
to know how you felt about me back then.
To hear it.
To know you saw me.
I did the best I could.
We always do our best,
but it's never enough.
Mm-hmm.
Success has been my biggest failure.
I'd trade everything to give Camila
and Lorenzo what you gave us.
Come on. Chin up.
This is a party.
Depression's a bourgeois illness,
fruit of too much leisure.
We've got no time for sorrow. Hmm?
I see you every day.
I feel you close to me
because I let you go.
I miss your big hands, your clean scent.
I miss our talks.
You always brought out the best in me.
I'm always here, son,
whenever you need me.
I still can't let Mateo go.
You'll eventually learn how.
Life is just a brief series
of senseless events.
You must surrender to it.
Clench your fists.
Hold your head high.
Let's drown our shame with a drink
and toast to your success.
- Cheers.
Remember what I always told you?
Take a swig of success.
Swish it around, and spit it out.
Otherwise, it'll poison you.
Who's there?
Hi, Ma.
What a surprise.
I didn't know you were coming.
Yes, I called you yesterday.
We talked for a good while.
I said I'd be here today.
Did you talk
to your brother and sisters?
I saw them at the party.
The party?
The Mexican journalists
held a tribute for me.
I was going to invite you, but I thought...
I thought
you'd come with the kids.
How are Camila and Mateo?
Lorenzo.
Camila and Lorenzo.
Ah. What did I say?
Mateo.
Impossible.
Your Mateo was born dead.
He wasn't born dead, Mama.
He lived for a day, 30 hours.
That's not living.
Just like this isn't living.
I should be dead.
Mama, you've been saying that
for ten years.
Everyone's croaked, and you're still here.
What'd you do yesterday?
We went to the movies.
With Aunt Elvira
and her friends from the nursing home?
Yeah. Mm-hmm.
And?
A bunch of old people.
Really boring.
What did you expect?
People like me.
My age.
Something weird happened.
What?
- I went to the bathroom in the cinema...
- Oh?
You won't believe it.
My bed was in there.
Someone had put my whole bedroom in there.
- You must have dreamed that.
- No, son.
Someone took my home to the cinema.
There it is... outside.
All I wanted was to see
the end of the movie.
We're at your home, Ma.
Come on, let's look at the patio.
See how the shrub blossomed?
- Huh?
- Yeah.
This is your patio.
This is your house.
Mm-hmm.
How are things with Susana?
Oh, son.
This maid is robbing me.
She's not a maid. She's your nurse.
Yeah. These people are all the same.
Susana's educated. She's a professional.
Why do you look down on her?
A few days ago, your papa
brought me some bracelets
that belonged to your grandmother.
And now I can't find them.
Papa died eight years ago.
No, he didn't.
He died, Mama.
What are you saying?
I saw your father
at Christmas at your brother's house.
He wouldn't talk to me.
He must have been angry,
or he's with some other woman.
He comes to see me now and then.
When I'm sleeping on my stomach,
he grabs me by the legs.
Then he lulls me with his song.
What song?
- Oh, I don't remember.
- Mm.
It's that...
...the first time I made love
with your dad, we listened to that song.
And then... he'd whistle it to you
when you were in my belly.
And when you were little,
and you'd scream and throw tantrums,
he'd whistle that song to you,
and you'd calm down.
Really? I don't remember.
I don't remember anything
from my childhood.
Who sang it?
It was by Agustín Lara or... Pérez Prado.
Doesn't ring a bell.
Talk with your mouth, son.
You're driving me crazy.
Sorry.
But try and remember the song, Mama.
Who sang it?
The selfish man took it with him.
Excuse me.
Good afternoon, sir.
What'll you have?
We've got tripe, campechano...
Give me two beef tongue, please.
Coming right up.
- With everything?
- Yeah, everything.
- Are you okay?
- Yes.
- Do you need help?
- No.
- Let me...
- Don't touch me!
What's up with her?
- I don't know.
- Is she dead?
I'm not dead.
I'm missing.
- But you are right here, miss.
- Leave her. They do this.
They go missing,
yet they keep pestering everyone.
They neither return nor die.
Miss, what's going on? Tell me.
I can't.
They stay by not staying.
All they do is complain, buddy.
Please, tell me what's wrong.
Trust me, it's best not to know.
Martín!
Hey!
Police!
Ideas ate the deities!
The deities became ideas!
Great bladders full of bile!
The bladders burst!
The idols exploded!
Putrefaction of deities!
Swarm of flies!
The sanctuary was a dung heap!
The dung heap a nursery!
Armed ideas sprouted,
idealized ideodeities,
sharpened syllogisms!
Cannibal deities!
Ideas idiotic as deities.
Rabid dogs.
Dogs in love with their own vomit.
We have dug up rage.
The amphitheater of the genital sun
is a dung heap.
A dead country where none of us die.
Who do you think you are,
stealing Octavio Paz's ideas?
His words exist
because I existed, Silverio.
Don't make me laugh,
Hernán Cortés.
You were just a thug,
a jackal with a machete,
slicing blindly through the jungle.
- There's not a single book in your body.
- You don't know me.
- No one knows me.
- Eh.
If your sense of shame was proportional
to the disaster your conquest wrought,
maybe you'd be a bit humbler.
Nah.
Got a light?
I know what you're thinking.
Five hundred years people have blamed me
without understanding shit.
- Don't you realize where you're sitting?
- Don't you? Look around.
The most beautiful city,
inhabited by 300,000 Indians.
- They weren't Indians.
- Americans, then.
- Still wrong.
- Whatever.
How could 400 Spaniards with 16 horsemen
and a little gunpowder trample an empire?
- Those Indians...
- They weren't Indians!
Cannibals, whatever.
They ate each other like savages.
They all hated each other.
And they all hated the tlatoani.
In that corner right there,
I met Moctezuma.
- Good dude.
- No.
Yeah.
That corner right there
is where we discovered Europe.
We were just trying to help you.
We gave you our God and our language.
And smallpox and measles
and the fear of hell.
And gonorrhea.
And your army
and the oligarchy and your church
and 300 years of
the ugliest fucking viceroys imaginable!
Look at our god Centéotl.
You buried our gods
and brought us a new one, still bloody,
tortured, and crucified.
Don't be a moron, Cortés.
You were nothing more
than a useful foreigner.
It's easy to win a war when the enemy,
our people, betrays and attacks itself.
I never wanted war.
I fell in love with this land
and its people.
Pretty words from the mouth of a murderer.
Murderer?
I laid the foundations for a new world.
My children were the first Mexicans,
so I am your father, like it or not.
I lived a Mexican,
and I died more Mexican than anyone.
I'm sorry to say, people hate you
as much in Mexico as they do in Spain.
There's not a single statue of you.
Sometimes we think
we're from several places,
when in fact, we're from nowhere.
Maybe hatred is every great man's fate.
And quit with
the childish tantrums, Silverio.
Why are you so mad?
It's not like you're an Indian,
mulatto, mongrel.
Look at yourself, you're more Creole
and Mestizo than my own children.
You don't want to be Indians.
Or Spaniards.
You've willfully condemned
yourselves to bastardy,
to coexist in limbo.
For fuck's sake.
Turn that shit off! You're gonna blind me!
What is it?
- He burned me with that cigarette!
- Don't move.
Don't move. Don't move.
Stop moving! Stay still!
We're doing another take!
Cut! Martín!
Martín, don't let anyone move
for Christ's sake!
What's up, cabrón?
- Five minutes!
- Wait!
Dead and missing people
to your positions!
Martín, we're doing
another take. Everyone, stay still!
Goddammit!
I'm good. Nah,
I'm here shooting with a cocky director.
One of those movies about
Hernán Cortés or some bullshit.
Sube, Pelayo, sube!
Nice fucking house, man.
Did Pablo Galindo ask you for rent?
He just lent it to me
for a couple of days.
Rich people don't do anything for free.
That's why they're rich.
This is gorgeous.
He will charge for this
one way or another.
Hortensia and I are going
to the club to get our beach stuff.
- On my way. Get Lorenzo.
- Lorenzo is taking a nap.
No. There'll be time to nap later.
Life's rich with rich friends, brother.
I'm going to the beach
before you start breaking my balls.
Just don't steal the flatware, cabrones!
- Only the real silver!
- Or some nice wine!
Good morning, sir.
Go on ahead.
Pa!
Come here!
- What's up?
- This man won't let Hortensia in.
Why? Is there a problem?
- Servants can't enter.
- She's family.
Rules of the place.
Can't you make an exception?
We're guests of Pablo Galindo.
We're staying at his home...
Sorry, sir.
But all the owners agreed to the rule.
Servants can't use the facilities.
Not even to walk the beach?
I'm sorry, miss.
Who's your superior?
He's off today.
- Hortensia, go home...
- No! If Hortensia can't go, no one will.
- Those are the rules of the place.
- You have to do something. At least...
Those are the rules of the place!
- I'll call Pablo, and...
- Why bother, sir?
It's those rich people who make the rules.
Let's get out of here.
Stick your beach up your ass, then!
- It's official.
- What?
Amazon just bought Baja California.
- This beach now belongs to the gringos.
- Amazing!
Let them buy all of Mexico.
We will be better off.
I had no idea that people
in my own family were so unpatriotic.
Imagine what it would be like...
What?
You seem famished.
The fruit tastes like fruit here.
How are you?
Fine.
Mom wants to go to the beach.
She says it's a way off.
- She wants to get there before sundown.
- We'll leave soon.
But tell me, how are things?
- What things?
- How's everything in Boston?
- You still with Mark?
- Yeah.
Hmm? You don't sound convinced.
- It's not that.
- Hmm.
- Everything's fine with Mark.
- Ah.
Not everything. I mean, it never is, but...
I hadn't thought about Mark
until you said his name.
Well then?
I don't know.
It's weird being here.
Where? On the beach?
In Mexico.
I don't get it.
You do.
Why? Your cousins are here,
your aunts and uncles...
- Exactly.
- Exactly what?
It's everything that never was.
And seeing them reminds me of that.
Everything that wasn't.
Yeah. Including Mateo.
Mateo's not the only one in Bardo, Pa.
Sometimes I feel like we're all with him.
Camila, your family will always be here.
Your home's here, your grandparents...
Dad, stop, I am fine. I am just sad!
And that's okay.
Feeling sad is good for you sometimes.
But you always want to fix things,
explain them away.
Some things just are what they are.
My lease is up next month.
Mm?
- I was thinking of coming back to Mexico.
- Why?
- To live here.
- What about your job in Boston?
The job's fine,
but I can't grow there anymore.
I am tired of eating a salad
on a plastic tray alone at my desk.
What will you do in Mexico?
I don't know.
I like the idea,
but you'll have
to get used to being way more careful.
My friends live here,
and nothing's ever happened to them.
Because they live
in a gated community
with guards all around,
and drivers take them everywhere.
Are you up for that? I'm not.
At least they don't live
in a pasteurized reality like us.
A pasteurized reality where you can walk
around at night or take public transit.
You've never used public transportation.
- I use it.
- Come on.
Where's the Santa Monica train stop?
Between Ocean and Venice.
Wrong.
How much is a ticket?
- I don't know.
- Of course you don't.
We're grown-ups, Pa.
We're free to choose where to live.
Okay?
Camila, you know I'm here for anything.
But you can't ask me
not to want the best for you.
Get a move on. It's getting late.
Sometimes what's best for you
isn't what's best for us.
Let's go before Mama chews us out.
How's that going?
It's going.
Hey, tell me if you want to invite
Jon and Stephen.
Pa...
- Hmm?
- Remember Paco?
Who?
Paco, Guido, and Ernesto.
- My axolotls. When we lived in Mexico.
- Yeah, sure.
Well, when I was a kid
and we moved to LA, I brought them with us
'cause I left all my friends in Mexico.
So I decided to hide Paco,
Guido, and Ernesto in a suitcase
with a plastic bag and water.
I didn't tell anyone.
And when we arrived to the new house,
the first thing I did
was open the suitcase.
It was soaking wet,
and the plastic bag was open,
and my friends were lost in the clothes.
And they didn't move,
so I decided to throw them in the toilet
to see if they could swim.
And they sank.
So I realized they were dead,
and I hid 'em in a shoebox under my bed.
After a few days, it started to smell,
so I put 'em in the freezer.
And, yeah, I remember Mom was cooking
some fish for dinner,
and I didn't even want to touch my food
'cause I was freaking out,
convinced that we were eating my friends.
What is it?
I never knew any of that.
Why didn't you tell me?
I think you were gone.
You were in Morocco doing something.
Or maybe you were home.
I don't know.
Doesn't matter.
If you find a bomb
lying around the airport premises,
please bring it
to the nearest information booth.
Thank you for your consideration.
Please refrain from turning left.
Hello, sir.
Please remove your glasses, sir.
- What is the purpose of your trip?
- We live here.
No, you don't live here.
Fingerprints.
Oh, yes. We do live here.
I'm a journalist, and this is my home.
This is not your home, sir.
You have an O-1 visa.
Please look at the camera.
Yeah, I have an O-1 visa
because I work here and I pay taxes here.
- So I think I can call this place my home.
- Fingerprints.
No, sir,
you cannot call this place your home.
If you look me in the face,
you might recognize me...
- We speak English.
- Dad.
What's your name?
- Excuse me?
- Your name.
Drop it.
- Remove your arm, sir.
- I want to talk to your supervisor.
That will not be necessary.
Oh,
"That will not be necessary."
You can go now.
Next.
Asshole. Come on.
Let's go.
Excuse me?
- Are you a supervisor?
- Yes, I am.
That officer was very rude to me.
I've been living here for 15 years,
and he says I have not the right
to call this my home.
It was very upsetting.
- What is your status here, sir?
- I have an O-1 visa.
Then yes, you can call this your home.
Well, if he's the face of this nation,
then you should do something.
It was very humiliating.
I'm sorry about this, sir.
I'll take care of it.
The bastard should apologize.
This man is upset.
- He said you humiliated him.
- In no way was I disrespectful.
- He was aggressive.
- No, I need him to give us an apology.
- Sir, I'll take care of it.
- No, I need an apology.
What's up? Drop it.
No, I need this guy
to say this is our home.
- This is not your home, sir.
- What did you say?
- Those are the rules.
- What rules?
This person has an O-1 visa,
and his family, an O-3.
They're allowed to call this home.
- You hear that?
- Please apologize to them.
No, this is not their home.
They're not Americans.
What are you?
Mexican, Chinese, fucking Swedish?
- Sir.
- I grew up here. Went to school here.
- This is our home, you like it or not.
- Please control your son.
No!
He should shut up
and be respectful.
I'm tired of this bullshit
since I was a kid in this country.
Okay, if you want to call
this place your home, so be it.
Hey, look us in the eye.
- You can't talk to him like that.
- You speak Spanish?
- You look more Mexican than I do.
- Don't understand.
Are you afraid
they'll realize you're Mexican?
I'm American.
America is a continent, asshole.
We're all Americans too.
They stole our name.
- He understands.
- He hasn't apologized.
- Just fucking apologize.
- Say you're sorry.
- Say you are sorry.
- Say you are sorry!
- Don't touch me!
- Come on!
Say it!
Say you're sorry! Say it!
Lorenzo!
Papá!
This is a really nice home
you guys have.
Thank you.
Oh, you're very welcome.
Thank you. Have a good day.
Lorenzo, move your suitcase!
Okay, I'll do it.
I'm gonna take a walk.
I still have a headache.
Come here. Lie down for a bit.
See if you can change
the old walrus look on your face.
You can't go to the awards ceremony
looking like that.
They would have you believe
that Jesus Christ was a white man.
That's a lie.
Jesus wasn't no white man.
Jesus was a brown man!
And in fact,
truth be told, he was Palestinian.
Hey!
You believe in God, right?
You got faith, right?
Oh. Excuse me? Excuse me, sir?
Welcome aboard the Metro Expo Line.
This train's final destination is
Downtown Santa Monica station.
The next stop is Expo Park/USC station.
Now arriving.
Exit here for... California Science Center,
Natural History Museum.
No, leave them alone.
Leave me alone, Grandma.
Go, go. Dude.
Please stand clear.
The doors are closing.
Now arriving,
7th Street/Metro Center in Downtown LA.
As far as this train goes.
Please check...
Shit.
Sir...
Please check
you have all of your personal belongings.
You okay?
Hold on until the doors have opened.
Sir?
Are you okay, mister?
Do you need help?
Can I help you, sir?
I don't understand.
I don't understand you, sir.
Sir?
I don't understand you.
Juan! Juan!
911?
Good evening.
I'm proud to be here tonight,
representing my father
and our whole family.
The last few days have been
the saddest of my life,
but today I choose to be proud and happy.
I'm going to read you my father's speech.
He carried it with him.
"Dear colleagues
of the American Society of Journalists..."
That's all.
My father isn't big
on being in the spotlight.
One might say he suffered the stroke
to avoid coming to the ceremony.
He's probably
in his coma laughing at us.
Silverio Gama loves California.
He chose to live here
the last 20 years of his life.
And he chose to raise us here.
So I'm sure he's proud
this country he got used to calling home
is giving him such a prestigious award.
He also missed Mexico
every day of his life.
Before watching the video
his colleague and friend, Martín Solís,
edited for us tonight,
I would like to ask all of you
to please give a huge round of applause
to my father, this year's honoree,
Silverio Gama.
Come on, louder!
Louder!
Is that normal?
- What?
- That sound. Is it normal?
Yes, it's normal.
The sheets are soaked.
He's wet.
Maybe the bag was full.
I think they forgot to change it.
I'll call the nurse.
Do you see
any improvement, Doctor?
No. All we can do is wait.
There's a major hemorrhage in one lobe.
- This could take a long time.
- How long?
I don't know.
Do you think he's here with us?
Can he hear us?
Sure, he's here.
But at the same time, he's not.
A coma is basically a mystery, Camila.
What's he doing with his eyes?
It's a reflex.
It feels like he's squeezing
when I take his hand.
Yesterday we put on some music
and some recordings
from when we were kids,
and he cried a little.
Silverio...
Can you hear me?
Where are you?
I feel you can hear me.
Have you seen the remote?
No.
...the main subject in discussion,
off-the-record, the revolutionary sale.
Moving down the...
No one
lifted a finger to help him.
At the train's last stop,
he was the last passenger.
A cleaning lady found him.
A compatriot of ours,
Ms. Refugio Domínguez.
Hello, Refugio.
- Hi.
- We caught up with her.
We'll have the pleasure
of speaking with her.
Thanks for joining us.
Tell us what happened.
I went in to clean the car,
as usual, and saw it wasn't empty.
I thought the guy might be a drunk
because that's common here.
But then I saw the fish on the floor.
Silverio...
How are you feeling?
You seem tired.
Peaceful.
Tranquil.
What the fuck was my dad doing
on the Santa Monica train?
He wanted to feel more Mexican.
But with all those Mexicans around,
his head exploded.
You're such an asshole.
Something weird happened a few days ago
in our bedroom in Los Angeles.
I was sleeping on my stomach,
and something grabbed my feet
and started pulling.
It jerked me upward.
There was nothing I could do.
The dream was so real.
And I'm sure it happened
right when Silverio had his stroke.
Thanks for bringing him
to Mexico.
Hey, Pa!
Hey, Pa! What's the name of that song?
I don't remember the name,
but I love it.
You always do the same thing.
You take something away,
then you don't remember.
But Ma, you always danced
to that song with Papa.
Son, your father was a drag.
He never liked dancing,
and it's my favorite thing in the world.
Tough men don't dance.
I was comfortable
at home watching TV,
and look where you've taken me.
All I wanted was to see
the end of the movie.
Okay, Ma, but can someone tell me
the name of that song?
What are you talking about?
Brother, do you remember
the name of that song
Papa whistled to us when we were kids?
Where did you bring us, brother?
He never even whistled me a ranchera.
Don't leave again, darky.
Come back.
You're leaving without putting me
in one of your movies.
Not even as one of those extras.
Keep going!
- Where are you coming from?
- From the North!
From hell, but they don't even know
they're living in hell.
Where are you taking him?
To the South.
We'll use this piece to resuscitate him.
He will rebuild himself completely.
Let the whole world look to the south!
How do you know
it's in that direction?
Pa!
Lorenzo!
You need to go the other way!
No, Pa!
We're going with you!
Turn around!
There's nothing here for you!
And you?
I'll see you when I'm back!
When might that be?
When?
Papá!